Guide to the Seattle Veterans Action Center Records 1971-1981
Seattle Municipal Archives
Seattle Veterans Action Center Records
1971-1981
City of Seattle Seattle Municipal Archives PO Box 94728 600 Fourth Avenue, Floor 3 Seattle, WA 98124-4728 Phone: 206/233-7807 Email: archives@seattle.gov http://www.seattle.gov/cityarchives
3631-01
Seattle (Wash.). Human Services Dept.
2.2 cubic feet 6 boxes
Records of an agency serving Vietnam War veterans
Historical Note
An Office of Human Resources was established in 1971 in the Executive Department to develop, implement, and manage social services for low-income and disadvantaged residents of Seattle. In 1973 it was replaced by the Department of Human Resources. DHR administered family and youth services programs, senior citizen services, community service activities, the Seattle Veterans Action Center, and the Comprehensive Residential Weatherization Program. Federal, state, and local grants comprised two-thirds of the department's operating budget. Passage of the 1986 Low Income Housing Levy increased the City's funding and policy role in housing issues. In 1991, the agency name was changed to the Department of Human Services. A year later, the Department of Housing and Human Services was created, incorporating the City housing programs and Community Development Block Grant administration from the recently abolished Department of Community Development. DHHS programs included aging services, family and youth services, housing and community services, human services, and the City's education office. In 1999, the Office of Housing was established as an independent agency and DHHS was reorganized as the Human Services Department.
The Seattle Veterans Action Center was established in 1971 to provide coordinated readjustment assistance to veterans, especially minority, disadvantaged and disabled Vietnam war veterans. Services included job referrals; education, job and benefit counseling; emergency services and discharge review. Records include subject files, grant files, photographs, public information files, and reports. Subjects include amnesty for war resisters, creation of the Center, funding, and the Mayor's Committee To Aid Returning Veterans.
Arranged into five subseries: subject files, grant files, photographs, public relations files and reports.
Records are open to the public.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Seattle (Wash.). Dept. of Human Resources; National League of Cities
Seattle (Wash.)
Veterans--Services for--United States; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Veterans--Washington--Seattle
Seattle
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Subject Files, 1971-1981
  - Action / VISTA Proposal for 1973-1975, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Amnesty, 1975 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Amnesty, 1976 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Amnesty, 1976 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Budget - Organization, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Budget, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Contributions To Sea-VAC, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Council of Churches (Washington), 1972 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Department of Human Resources Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Department of Human Resources Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Department of Human Resources Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Discharge Upgrade Project, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Employment (Jobs) Information, 1980 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Employment Project Study, 1975 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - EX-V-IT Program (Ex-Veteran-In-Training), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Film and Film Orders, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - History (Sea-VAC), 1981 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Incoming Letters, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Legislation (National), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Mayor's Committee To Aid Returning Veterans, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Mayor's Committee To Aid Returning Veterans, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Mayor's Committee To Aid Returning Veterans, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Mayor's Task Force To Aid Returning Veterans - Evaluation of Sea-VAC, 1973 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors Veterans Projects, 1976 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Outreach Plan, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Overviews and Attachments, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Private Industry Council Grant - Veterans Helping Veterans, 1980 (2/16)
  - Program Description, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Research Work, 1976 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Vietnam Veterans Civic Council, 1976 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Vietnam Veterans Coordinating Council, 1979 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Grant Files, 1971-1977
  - Proposals and Grants Office of Human Resources, 1971 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Proposals and Grants, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Proposals and Grants, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Proposals and Grants, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Proposals and Grants, 1974 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Proposals and Grants, 1975 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Proposals and Grants: National League of Cities, Creating Sea-VAC, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Grant Application: National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Proposals and Grants: National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Proposals and Grants: National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Proposals and Grants: National League of Cities / U.S. Conference of Mayors, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Proposals and Grants: Office of Economic Opportunity, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Proposals and Grants: Community Services Administration (OEO), 1974-1975 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Proposals and Grants: Community Services Administration (OEO), 1975 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Proposals and Grants: Community Services Administration, NOGA, 1976 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Proposals and Grants: Community Services Administration (OEO), 1976 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Proposals and Grants: Community Services Administration (OEO) Progress Reports, 1976 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Grant Application (Federal, OEO), 1977 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Proposals and Grants: OEO Veteran's Outreach, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Proposals and Grants: OEO Veteran's Outreach, 1973 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Proposals and Grants: OEO Veteran's Outreach, 1974 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Proposals and Grants: OEO Veteran's Outreach, 1974 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Proposal: Upward Bound, 1975 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Veterans Outreach Budget, 1973 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Sea-VAC Funding, Letters of Support, 1972 (Box-folder 4/14)
- Photographs (Mostly of Sea Vac Staff), undated (4/15)
- Public Relations Files, 1972-1978
  - Articles About Sea-VAC, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Press Releases, 1972 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Press Releases, 1972 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Press Releases, 1973 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Press Releases, 1973 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Press Releases, 1976 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Public Relations, 1974 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Public Relations, 1976 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Publicity, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Radio Releases: Public Service Announcements, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Radio Releases: Public Service Announcements, 1972 (Box-folder 5/11)
- Reports, 1972-1980
  - Reports - Annual, 1972-1980 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Reports DHR Bi Monthly, 1976 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Reports - Discharge Upgrade, National League of Cities, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Report - First Year, 1972 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Report - Two Year, 1973 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Reports - Less Than Honorable Cases, 1976 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Report - OEO, Evaluation of Sea-VAC, 1974 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Reports - Other-Than-Honorable Cases, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Report - Upward Bound, 1975 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Report - Veterans Rehabilitation Study, Interim Report, Undated (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Report - Women Veterans Project Final Report, 1980 (Box-folder 6/11)